james.coons@yahoo.com

Louisville, KY • Cell: 502-220-8569

Professional Profile

Solution-Driven Business Analyst with TWENTY years of experience using analytical skills and passion to help solve "Big Picture" business problems and then to provide efficient business solutions. Strong design, organization, verbal and

written communications skills and enjoy working as a team on projects. Skills include Requirements Gathering, User Acceptance Testing, Customer requirement eliciting and translating into business solutions. Access, Excel, ETL, SQL, VBA, SSMS, SSRS, SSIS, ADO, DAO, KPI, UAT, Agile.

Professional Experience

Multiple Clients, Freelancer – Multiple Roles, Louisville, KY

10/2017 to 06/2020

- Business Analyst (National Supply Network, 05/2017 to 12/2017) Created a Contact Management System (CMS); Created Smart Search to locate customer records, reduce errors and improve efficiency. (Access, VBA, SQL).
- Business Analyst (Piedmont Airlines, 11/2017 to 03/2020) Identified failure points in airport operations to improve effectiveness. Extracted and imported customer data into Access Tables. (Access, Excel, SQL).
- Algebra Tutor (private, 02/2020 to 06/2020) Tutored a college student (nursing) in algebra, including polynomial / quadratic / linear equations (long division, factoring, zeroes, solving, quadratic equation, inequalities, domain, range, graphing), logarithms and composite functions. Total 68 hours done via Zoom due to COVID. Student received a B on her final exam.

Ryder Integrated Logistics, Business Analyst, Georgetown, KY

02/2015 to 06/2015

Improved management decisions at Toyota by creating dashboard of driver schedules, driving history, route data and other KPIs for inbound transportation to Toyota Manufacturing (SQL, VBA, SSMS, SSRS, SSIS, ADO, DAO, ETL). Contract Position via SGS (Software Galaxy Systems).

- Decreased Costs by tracking driver speed, fuel usage, excessive idling and On-Time history.
- Developed Dashboards, Score Cards and Reports to monitor driver performance using SQL Services.
- Created automated system to import, analyze, validate and export performance data from external systems.

Department of Defense (SSB), Business Analyst, **Lexington**, **KY**

08/2011 to 06/2014

Reverse-engineered existing ordering System into a web-based logistics application to improve speed and accuracy, teaming up with Business Analysts in Lexington and the Development Team at the Pentagon (Dept of Defense).

- Gathered requirements from key stakeholders, including Programmers at the Pentagon.
- Created Functional Requirements, Business Rules, As-Is Docs, To-Be Docs, Use Cases, Test Cases, Story Boards, Test Plans and End-User Acceptance Testing (UAT).
- Created and maintained the User Guide.
- Participated in JAD/SCRUM/SPRINT sessions (Agile / SDLC method) and Waterfall Methodologies.

Core Logic, Business Analyst / Contractor, Louisville, KY

12/2010 to 04/2011

Worked with off-shore programming team in India on Mortgage products (Loss Mitigation, Foreclosure, Bankruptcy).

- Designed data export of customer's files, including technical specifications, SQL Server Tables, Stored Procedures, data encryption, data export and transportation to FTP site.
- Wrote Technical Specifications and Documentation for Loss Mitigation Plans.
- Analyzed customer's Business Rules and created Business Requirements for software development.
- Created SQL Server Report for use by customers.

Multiple Clients, Business Analyst (Freelance), Louisville, KY

04/2010 to 12/2010

Created website for customer; created a Contact Management System and updated a customer's website.

- Created website for customer's web presence (The Kircher Group, Mast Construction).
- Updated customer's website to provide a fresh format (www.ChileMission.org).
- Created "JobEx" Contact Management System with calendar and reminders in Excel and VBA (personal).
- Designed "web-scraping" techniques to pull website data into Excel (VBA, macros).

Quilogy, Business Analyst, Louisville, KY

07/2008 to 01/2010

Business Analyst on Multiple team projects. Later Aspect Software. (SharePoint, InfoPath, SQL, VBA, SSMS, Agile).

- Created a Web Site Provisioning System for KCTCS University (SharePoint, InfoPath, Agile, SCRUM).
- Created a complex Human Resources system (SharePoint, Agile, InfoPath).
- Created training materials and used to teach 12 classes (SharePoint, Nintex Workflows).
- Created procedure to convert 110,000 files from DocuShare into SharePoint (SharePoint, Nintex Workflows).
- Created training course (25 lessons) for KCTCS instructors (16 colleges, 68 campuses) (SharePoint, Word).
- Converted data for MicroSoft's Amalga healthcare system (SQL, SSIS, Excel).

Temp Work, Temp Manufacturing Positions, Louisville, KY

08/2006 to 07/2008

Multiple temporary positions after returning from Chile, including assembly line, technician and inventory system.

- Assembly Line (Greenlee-Textron through Willstaff Worldwide).
- Dell Diagnostic Technician (Trillium Industries through Robert Half International).
- Warehouse (International Moulding Company); Inventory system (Excel, VBA).

Chile Mission, Website Designer / Missionary, Santiago, Chile

01/2005 to 08/2006

Created website for the mission in Santiago, Chile; performed budget and expense administration. (FrontPage, Word, Excel).

- Created the mission's website to provide information for visitors.
- Taught English classes to attract people to the Mission.
- Performed administrative functions, including Missions budgets and expenses (MS Excel, Word and PowerPoint).

Master Data Center, Business Analyst, Southfield, MI

04/1995 to 10/2004

Converted customer's data and imported into the company's Intellectual Property Management Database; created ProSpec data conversion system. Later **Thompson IP Management**, then **Clarivate**. (Access, Excel, VBA, SQL, ETL).

- Improved data conversion process by creating ProSpec Tool in MS Access (VBA, ADO, T-SQL). Wrote User Manual.
- Created 30+ data conversion tools used by programmers (VB, VBA, COBOL, DOS, QuickBasic).
- Saved estimated \$3,000 on a data conversion project using the ProSpec tool (reduced conversion process time by 75%) and subsequently achieved similar time savings on all subsequent projects.
- Trained programmers on data conversion processes and techniques.

Department of Defense (CDSI), Business Analyst, Indiana / Michigan

12/1991 to 03/1995

Dept of Defense projects included payroll automation and M1-Abrams tank tracking. (Clipper, dBase, Word).

- DFAS, Fort Harrison, IN: Automated Base Pay, Recruitment and Allowance Systems. Wrote User Manual.
- TACOM, Warren, MI: Designed and programmed "Project Sword" logistics system to track M1-Abrams tanks as they moved from Production to the customer Site in Saudi Arabia. Wrote User Manual.
- Corps of Engineers, Detroit, MI: Provided network support to Users at Corps of Engineers office. Saved customer \$2,500 by recovering 6 weeks of data from a corrupt insurance file.

Other Experience

Lucky's Market	Culinary Associate	Louisville, KY	09/2017 to 02/2020
Red Carpet Inn	Front Desk Associate	Louisville, KY	12/2016 to 02/2017
Direct Insurance Marketing Assoc.	Life Insurance Interviewer	Louisville, KY	08/2016 to 10/2016

Education

Associate's Degree, Info. Systems	ITT Technical Institute	Indianapolis, IN
Bachelor's Degree, Management	Indiana Wesleyan University	Indianapolis, IN

Skills

•	<u>Software</u> :	MicroSoft Office, SharePoint, Visual Studio, Nintex Workflows, Active Server Pages, PowerPoint.
•	Programming:	Visual Basic 6.0, Visual Basic for Applications, Active Server Pages, Basic JavaScript, CSS, HTML.

■ <u>Databases</u>: MicroSoft SQL Server, Stored Procedures, SSIS, SSRS, T-SQL, MS Access, FoxPro, dBase.

■ Processes: Data Analysis, ETL, Data Mapping, Agile, Scrum, Sprint, Use Case, User Stories, SDLC.

Industries: U.S. Army Department of Defense, Government, Logistics, Transportation, Banking, Mortgage,
Intellectual Property, Insurance, Freelancing, Consulting.